hey folks Bret here I wanted to take a
crack at analyzing the steven crowder
situation for those who don't know
Crowder has a very popular YouTube
channel with more than three million
subscribers which was recently
demonetised by Google for what it said
for violations of its Terms of Service
in particular Crowder mocked Fox
reporter Carlos Massa
who is gay and he did so in a way that
was quite mean-spirited now many have
pointed out that others have done far
worse on YouTube and not had their
channels d monetized so what's going on
well the key concept is selective
enforcement or what I call the principle
of the low posted speed limit you can
imagine a town in which a speed limit
was posted so low that people routinely
violated as they pass through town and
the enforcement authority can decide if
it wants to pull over black people or
gay people or Jews or hippies or
whatever it doesn't like the law itself
isn't biased but the enforcement makes
it as if it were so in one sense because
Crowder is such a big target he is
facing a kind of enforcement that may
not be seen elsewhere now there is an
important issue here which has to do
with the question of speech is steven
crowder engaged in an act of free speech
that is in some way protected well
technically not the First Amendment does
not apply to Google because Google is a
private corporation on the other hand
the First Amendment was designed to
protect free expression the reason that
it is very specifically limited to
governmental interference is that the
founders in particular feared
governmental tyranny we don't know what
they would have thought about tech
platforms but my guess is the very same
logic that led them to build multiple
protections into the US Constitution
against government overreach would have
caused them if they had understood the
way Silicon Valley would function to
protect us also from these tech
platforms and their disproportionate
power but the founders were simply not
gods and they couldn't look forward in
such a way and so they left us with a
situation in which we know what they
were trying to protect us
but the map they gave us was not
sufficient to do the job in the 21st
century we should also recognize when we
talk about these corporations that they
are not one thing in fact we can
recognize several different layers at
work in these processes there is the
speech layer the part of Twitter or
YouTube where we the public talk to each
other there is the algorithm layer which
decides what we see is in general
functioning in an automatic way but it
may be climbed to have certain biases
within it and then there's the corporate
layer where something that we can't
engage with talks to itself and decides
what it is trying to accomplish
presumably the corporate layer is
divided there may be a big difference
between the people who are attempting to
steer the corporation in the direction
of profitability and let's say the truth
and safety committee within the
corporation that may have a different
agenda unfortunately we don't get much
of a window into the discussion between
those two layers but it is worth keeping
in mind that as Google takes action it
may not be of one mind let us assume for
the moment that most of us believe in
the concept not only of free speech but
in the value that is being protected by
the First Amendment free expression some
of us have been cast as free speech
absolutist and in fact I've used that
term with reference to myself others
like my brother Eric Weinstein has
argued he's not a free speech absolutist
because he is concerned about certain
things that might be protected by such a
none nuanced view now we can debate the
merits of free speech absolutism but
even those of us who favor it don't do
so naively the fact is free speech
absolutism results in the protection of
some things that we would much prefer
not be protected the reason that we fall
out is free speech absolutist in any
event is because there is no way to draw
the line so that it does not do damage
and I think I speak for most of those in
this
camp when I say but we have recognized
is that the harm done by attempting to
draw the line tends to be much greater
than the benefit of drawing the line and
so in the end we are better off
accepting that harm than attempting to
create a border where we will eventually
do violence if you don't know what I'm
talking about consider the question of
dead naming when a person has
transitioned from one sex to the other
there is a principle I believe it is
part of Twitter's Terms of Service at
this point that dead naming them is
considered a violation dead naming is
simply the act of invoking the name that
somebody had before they went through
their transition now in principle I
would agree that it's not a very nice
thing to do and in general when somebody
says they want to be called by a
particular name from here on out I see
no reason that we shouldn't honor that
request on the other hand there are
places where we must not honor that
request and we are beginning to lose
sight of this I noticed one particular
instance recently when Julian Assange
was arrested that arrest caused a spate
of news reports to come out and those
news reports tended to recount the
history of WikiLeaks I noticed in the
New York Times and in Rolling Stone in
particular those reports said that
Chelsea Manning had handed documents to
Julian Assange which had resulted in
Manning's prosecution now that's not a
description of what took place in
history
in fact Bradley Manning was the person
who was convicted of having handed
secret documents to Julian Assange not
Chelsea Manning the transition happened
after he had already been convicted for
the New York Times and Rolling Stone to
report that Chelsea Manning had done
this is simply an inaccurate reporting
of the facts on the other hand it might
be argued that my even invoking the name
Bradley Manning was somehow a violation
of the Terms of Service of the entity I
would use to distribute the video well
that can't be we have to get back to a
state where even if I wish to honor
Chelsea Manning's
to be called Chelsea Manning when we get
to questions of history I am allowed to
invoke her former identity as Bradley
Manning as it is an important historical
fact and an unchangeable one so let's
move on to the question of steven
crowder in the interest of full
disclosure I should tell you that months
ago Stephen and might invited me on to
his program and I considered going I
asked him if we could do it in person
because I felt like there were some
difficult things that I had to say to
him and I didn't want to do it over a
remote link he didn't want to do it in
person and so I let it go at that
the fact is I do think those things
still need to be said what Stephen did
to Carlos
Mozza is pretty nasty stuff and it's not
the only time he's done such a thing a
year or so ago
I saw a video in which Steven sent a
Confederate into a meeting of trans
people and the Confederate filmed his
harassment of them presumably for
comedic purposes but the whole thing
struck me as so mean-spirited that I
couldn't see any justification for it
these people were not acting in public
in some way that required commentary
these people were simply meeting to
discuss things and it wasn't really
Stevens right to disrupt that surely
people have a right to gather and have
discussions that are private without
Steven intervening on the other hand
having the tech platforms police
etiquette is turning into an absolute
nightmare and there's no way it's going
to end well in the end what's going to
happen is whatever rules they lay down
are going to be used by bad actors and
they are going to run roughshod over the
rest of us so what I'm going to suggest
is that we do something else
Steven I'm really talking to you here I
get a lot out of what you do on YouTube
in particular I'm very fond of the thing
you do where you set up a card table on
a college campus and you have a
principal stated on the sign and then
you ask people to convince you otherwise
I think that's a very valuable exercise
it happens I disagree with you a lot of
the time but it is
very informative to watch people
challenge you and frankly I think it's
quite humanizing but some of the stuff
you do where you you give people a hard
time over their sexual orientation or
other side of stuff I just don't see any
reason for it and I think frankly it's
time for you to outgrow it so in any
case I'd be willing to talk to you about
this but I hope you'll take it to heart
and think about just simply not be in a
dick hey folks if you like this video
click like subscribe to the channel and
if you feel like supporting the creation
of more content like this head on over
to my patreon page and sign up at
whatever level feels comfortable